Register of the Karl Baarslag papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Karl Baarslag papers
1919-1979
1940-1960
85040
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes (2.8 linear feet)
Writings, reports, memoranda, letters, pamphlets, and other printed matter relating to international communism, communism in the United States, communism in maritime unions, and internal security activities of the Office of Naval Intelligence during World War II.
Baarslag, Karl.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
The Church League of America Collection of the Research Files of Counterattack, the Wackenhut Corporation, and Karl Baarslag, Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Communist Party of the United States of America issuances, Hoover Institution Archives
Jay Lovestone papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1900 November 25 Born
1920s-1930s Marine radio operator
1935 Published SOS to the Rescue
1937 Published Coast Guard to the Rescue
1938 Published Robbery by Mail: The Story of the U.S. Postal Inspectors
1940 Published Islands of Adventure
1941-1945 Lieutenant commander, United States Navy; assigned to Office of Naval Intelligence
1947 Published Communist Trade Union Trickery Exposed
1947-1953 Head of the National Americanism Commission of the American Legion
1953-1954 Research director for the Senate Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations
1956-1960 Consultant for the House Committee on Un-American Activities
1984 January 10 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Karl Baarslag papers contain writings, reports, memoranda, letters, pamphlets, books, and other printed matter relating to international communism, communism in the United States, communism in maritime unions, and internal security activities of the Office of Naval Intelligence during World War II. Some of Baarslag's own writings on communism; chapters from his unpublished memoir, "Backwards, Turn Backwards;" and his writings on other research interests are also included in the papers.
The majority of the material is located in the Communist Activities File, which contains material documenting various domestic and international communist movements and organizations, such as the Communist Party of the United States of America, the International of Seamen and Harbour Workers (ISH), and the Marine Transport Workers of the Western Hemisphere. Of particular note are letters written between 1924 and 1949 by prominent members of the Communist Party USA, including Jay Lovestone and Alex Bail, located in the Communist Party of the United States of America file.
In addition, the collection contains several pamphlets and books relating to communism and socialism, located in the Printed Matter series.
United States Office of Naval Intelligence.; Communism--United States.; Internal security--United States.; Labor unions and communism.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- Biographical File, 1951, 1953
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains a copy of a U.S. News & World Report article about Baarslag's role in the American Legion and a letter introducing Baarslag to Joseph Ku, Political Adviser to the Chinese Embassy in Washington, D.C.
  - "Legion's 'Red Chase': Being Toned Down?," U.S. News & World Report, 1953 June 12 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Letter from Alfred Kohlberg to Joseph Ku re Karl Baarslag, 1951 January 2 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Correspondence, 1971, 1979
  - Launter, John, 1971 January 11 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Packard, W. H., 1979 December 6 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Writings, 1940-1959, 1970-1973, undated
  Contains articles and drafts of books written by Baarslag. Also included are chapters from Baarslag's unpublished memoir, "Backwards, Turn Backwards." Arranged chronologically.
  - "Backwards, Turn Backwards,", undated
    - "Part I: Office of Naval Intelligence" (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - "Part III: Operations Overlord and C.I.O.S. [Combined Intelligence Objectives Sub-Committee of Shaef]" (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - "Part IV: Through the Siegfried Line and across the Rhine" (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - "Part V: What Has Really Happened to the American Legion?" (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - "Part XI: The Western Ocean Freighter Life on the North Atlantic" (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - "Part XV: Our Unknown Anti-Communist Dead" (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - "A Brief Memorandum on Communist Tactics,", undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - "Have the Communists Yet Stopped Their Cold War Against the U.S.?,", undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "Iron Curtain Visitors," manuscript, undated (Box-folder 1: 13-14)
  - "The Kronstadt Massacre of 1921,", undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - "Mutinies in Modern Navies," manuscript, undated (Box-folder 1: 16, Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "Riding the 'Reefers,'", undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - "Some Lessons from Byzanthium [sic],", undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - "Communists in Communication or Sovietizing American Citizens,", 1940 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - "What Have We Bought in Europe?,", 1953 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - "Womens International League for Peace and Freedom,", 1959 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "Chicago Trial and Red Tactics,", 1970 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - "The LaFollette Committee Unmasked,", 1970 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - "We Helped Industrialize Red Russia, Will We Make the Same Mistake with Red China?,", 1971 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - "Fallacies About Communism,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Writings by Others, 1945-1953, 1960, undated
  Contains articles and other writings mainly related to communism. Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - "Closest Brothers, Greatest Friendship,", 1960 December 13 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Colby, Bainbridge, "The New Deal Fifth Column,", undated (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Cronin, John, "The Problem of American Communism in 1945," (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Crouch, Paul, "Communist Infiltration of the American Armed Forces,", 1953 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Crouch, Paul, "Subversive Activities Control Board Docket No. 51-101,", 1951 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Donovan, William J. and Mary Gardiner Jones, "Program for a Democratic Counter Attack to Communist Penetration of Government Service,", 1949 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Hoover, J. Edgar, "An Analysis of the 17th National Convention of the Communist Party, USA,", 1960 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Kornfeder, Joseph, "Conquest by Subversion,", 1952 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Kornfeder, Joseph, "Infighting Amongst the Communists,", undated (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Lange, Alfred, "The Path to Victory: A Theoretical Discussion on Marxism and Insurrection,", undated (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Lorwin, Lewis L. and Jean A. Flexner, "International Transport Workers' Federation,", undated (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Speier, Hans, "The Proletariat and Its Critics,", undated (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Speier, Hans, "Tolstoy in the Marxist Mirror,", undated (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - "Summary of the House Intelligence Report that Was Never Published,", undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Tolley, Kemp, "Moscow at War,", undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Valtin, Jan, "Counter Revolution in Europe?,", undated (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Valtin, Jan, "How It Happened Last Time,", undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Communist Activities File, 1924-1971, undated
  Contains reports, memoranda, news clippings, collected correspondence, writings, and other material related to communism, communist groups, and communist activities in the U.S. and abroad.
  - "Action Conference on China Policy,", 1949 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - "Brief Historical Summary of the Russian War Relief,", undated (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - "Chinese Communist Publications Circulated in the United States,", undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Clippings, 1925-1961, undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
    Includes some clippings from the German publication Wir erobern die Betriebe, later known as Die Rote Fahne.
  - "Communist Fronts, Their History and Purpose,", circa 1961 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    Draft of a chapter later published in A Manual for Survival: A Counter-Subversive Study Course, produced by the Church League of America. Possibly written by Karl Baarslag.
  - Communist Party of the United States of America file, 1924-1961, undated
    Includes chronological files consisting primarily of collected correspondence of Party members, such as Jay Lovestone, Alex Bail, Bill Dunne, Max Bedacht, and Jack Stachel. Following the chronological files are documents, such as histories of the organization, bulletins, lists, and reports that are arranged alphabetically by document title or topic.
    - Undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - 1924-1926 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - 1928-1929 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - 1935-1937 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - 1949 (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - "Chronology of the Communist Party, U.S.A. Case, November 22, 1950 to December 1, 1961,", undated (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - "Chronology of Conventions Leading Up to, and of, the Communist Party of the United States of America,", 1960 (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - "The Communist Party in the United States,", undated (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - "The Communist Party of the United States of America,", 1930 (Box-folder 3: 18)
    - Convention bulletins, 1956 (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - "A Guide for Communist Work Aboard Ship,", 1937 (Box-folder 3: 20)
    - Immigration and Naturalization Service (INS) report, 1949 April 13 (Box-folder 3: 21)
    - List of district offices and officers, undated (Box-folder 3: 22)
    - List of Party leaders by state, undated (Box-folder 3: 23)
    - Supreme Court case, 1961 (Box-folder 3: 24)
    - Miscellany, 1928, undated (Box-folder 3: 25)
      Contains handwritten notes, part of a bibliography of works related to the Communist Party of the U.S.A., and a statement of cash receipts and payments from 1928.
  - Delegates of the First Communist Party Convention in 1934, undated (Box-folder 3: 26)
    Contains a photocopy of a photograph of the delegates.
  - "Einheitsverband," photostat, undated (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - International of Seamen and Harbour Workers (ISH) file, 1931-1935 (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - "Inquiry on Racial Incitations Practiced by Communists,", 1949 (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - The Kronstadt Group: A Political Platform for the Peoples of the USSR, 1970 (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - Marine Transport Workers of the Western Hemisphere file, 1926 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Memoranda, 1954, 1957 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    Contains memoranda written by and for Baarslag regarding communists, communist organizations, and communist activities in the U.S. and abroad.
  - The Militant, 1960 July 4 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - National Conference for New Politics bulletins, 1967 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - National Youth Alliance file, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Naval Intelligence Operations file, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 4: 6-7)
    Contains memoranda, drafts of memoranda, and reports written or received by Baarslag regarding Naval internal security, communist groups, and communist activities during World War II.
  - "Review of World-Wide Communist Trends,", 1944 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Shipmates' Voice, 1935 July (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Simas Kudirka incident, 1970 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    Contains press releases, a report, and the published hearings related to the investigation of the events surrounding the attempted defection of a Lithuanian seaman, Simas Kudirka. Kudrika attempted to defect to the U.S. by jumping aboard the USCGC Vigilant while his mother ship was anchored near Martha's Vineyard in Massachusetts.
  - "Statement of Lt. Duane Thorin, U.S.N., Ret., Prepared for Delivery to Senate Special Preparedness Subcommittee,", undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - "The Struggle Against Imperialist War and the Tasks of the Communists: Resolution of the Sixth World Congress of the Communist International July - August, 1928,", 1934 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - "Testimony of William F. Hynes, Acting Capt. of Detectives, Los Angeles Police Dept. Commanding, Intelligence Bureau,", undated (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Miscellany, 1934, 1968, undated (Box-folder 4: 14)
    Contains a copy of the Waldorf Pledge, a section from V. I. Lenin Collected Works, and mailings from various labor groups.
- Printed Matter, 1917-1971, undated
  Contains pamphlets, books, periodicals, and a report related to communism and socialism in the U.S. and abroad. Includes both communist and anti-communist writings.
  - Pamphlets, 1917-1965, undated
    - 10th Political Conference of the Possev Weekly, 1958 (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - 15 Years of the Communist International, undated (Box-folder 4: 16)
    - 76 Questions and Answers on the Bolsheviks and the Soviets, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - The American Way to Jobs, Peace, Democracy, 1954 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - Beat the "Incitement to Disaffection" Bill!, 1935 (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - A Comment on the March Moscow Meeting, 1965 (Box-folder 4: 20)
    - Communism in Germany!, 1933 (Box-folder 4: 21)
    - Communism-World Revolution to Red Imperialism, undated (Box-folder 4: 22)
    - The Communist Nucleus: What It Is, How It Works, 1928 (Box-folder 4: 23)
    - The Communist Party: A Manual on Organization, 1935 (Box-folder 4: 24)
    - Communist Trickery, undated (Box-folder 4: 25)
    - The Constitution of the Union of Socialist Soviet Republics, 1924 (Box-folder 4: 26)
    - De Leon the Uncompromising, 1939 (Box-folder 4: 27)
    - The Devil and Jimmy Byrnes, 1948 (Box-folder 4: 28)
    - Disintegration of Military Morale, undated (Box-folder 4: 29)
    - Fair Play for Cuba Committee Summer '64, 1964 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - German Woman in Soviet Hands, 1950 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Grasp the Weapon of Culture!, 1951 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Guide to Readings on Communism, undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - International Peace/Disarmament Directory, 1963 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - Jesus as a Free Speech Victim, 1960 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - Joseph Stalin for Peaceful Coexistence: Postwar Interviews, 1951 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - The Kronstadt Revolt, 1942 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - The Meaning of Social-Fascism, undated (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - The New Soviet Constitution, 1936 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - The October Revolution and the Triumph of Socialism, undated (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - The Pacific Coast Maritime Strike, 1937 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - The Path of a Renegade: Why Earl Browder Was Expelled from the Communist Party, 1946 (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - The Port Huron Statement, 1964 (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - Preparing for October, 1917 (Box-folder 5: 15)
    - Problems of Art and Literature, 1950 (Box-folder 5: 16)
    - The Professional Informer, 1955 (Box-folder 5: 17)
    - Program of the Communist International, 1936 (Box-folder 5: 18)
    - Program for a Political Offensive Against World Communism, 1955 (Box-folder 5: 19)
    - The Red Baiting Racket and How It Works, 1948 (Box-folder 5: 20)
    - Revolution in Iraq, 1959 (Box-folder 5: 21)
    - The Role of Labor Unions in the Russian Revolution, undated (Box-folder 5: 22)
    - The Russian Revolution, undated (Box-folder 5: 23)
    - The Russification of the Baltic States, 1950 (Box-folder 5: 24)
    - The Secret Battalion, 1946 (Box-folder 5: 25)
    - Soviet Penetration of Latin America Chile: The Allende Regime and Its Aftermath, undated (Box-folder 5: 26)
    - Stalin's Speeches on the American Communist Party, 1929 (Box-folder 5: 27)
    - The Struggle Against Imperialist War and the Tasks of the Communists, 1928 (Box-folder 5: 28)
    - The Struggle of the Marine Workers, undated (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Support the People of Viet Nam, Defeat U.S. Aggressors, Part I, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Support the People of Viet Nam, Defeat U.S. Aggressors, Part IV, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - The Telephone and Telegraph Workers, 1935 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - Text of Speeches by V. M. Molotov on General Reduction of Armaments at the General Assembly of the United Nations, 1946 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - The Trade Union Unity League, undated (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - The Truth About Communism in Hawaii, 1947 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - The Twenty-One Conditions of Admission Into the Communist International, undated (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - Under Arrest: Workers' Self-Defense in the Courts, undated (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - The United Front Against Fascism and War, undated (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - What Is Happening to the Jews in Soviet Russia?, 1951 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - Why Am I a Revolutionist?, undated (Box-folder 6: 12)
    - Why Communism?, 1934 (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - Periodicals, 1929, 1934, 1967
    - Information Bulletin, World Marxist Review Publishers, 1967 (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - Information Bulletin of the I.S.H. [International of Seamen and Harbour Workers], 1934 (Box-folder 6: 15)
    - The Red International of Labour Unions 1, nos. 8-9, 1929 October (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Report, Democrat Duplicity and Appeasement in Foreign Policy Administration, 1935-1947, as Revealed in the Memoirs of Official Participants, 1948 July (Box-folder 6: 17)
  - Books, 1932-1971, undated
    - 24th Congress of the CPSU [Communist Party of the Soviet Union] Information Bulletin 9, nos. 7-8, 1971 (Box-folder 6: 18)
    - Aptheker, Herbert, The Negro People in America, 1946 (Box-folder 6: 19)
    - Balabanoff, Angelica, Impressions of Lenin, 1968 (Box-folder 6: 20)
    - Buchner, Johannes, The Agent Provocateur in the Labor Movement, photocopy, undated (Box-folder 6: 21)
    - Ciliberti, Charles, Backstairs Mission in Moscow, 1946 (Box 7)
    - Communist Perspective: A Handbook of Communist Doctrinal Statements in the Original Russian and in English, undated
    - Foster, William Z., The New Europe, 1947
    - Huberman, Leo, The Labor Spy Racket, 1937
    - Johnson, Hewlett, The Secret of Soviet Strength, 1943
    - Khrushchev, N. S., Report on the Program of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, 1961 October 17
    - The Life of Stalin: A Symposium, 1932
    - Liu Shao-Chi, How to Be a Good Communist, 1952
    - Liu Shao-Chi, On the Party, 1950
    - Morrow, Felix, Revolution and Counter-Revolution in Spain, 1938
    - New Program of the Communist Party U.S.A.: A Draft, 1966
    - New Program of the Communist Party U.S.A., 1970
    - Niemeyer, Gerhart, Communists in Coalition Governments, circa 1963
    - Royal Institute of International Affairs, Soviet-Yugoslav Dispute, 1948
    - Snow, John Kowland, The Case of Tyler Kent, 1962
    - Stalin, Joseph, Problems of Leninism, 1935